<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD Specification V2.6//EN"
               "http://www.w3.org/2002/xmlspec/dtd/2.6/xmlspec.dtd" [
  <!-- ================================================================ -->
  <!ENTITY draft.day "9">
  <!ENTITY draft.DD "09">
  <!ENTITY draft.month "01">
  <!ENTITY draft.monthname "January">
  <!ENTITY draft.year "2006">
  <!ENTITY iso6.doc.date "&draft.year;-&draft.month;-&draft.DD;">
  <!ENTITY http-ident "http://www.w3.org/2001/tag/doc/namespaceState">
]>
<spec w3c-doctype='other'>
<?CVS $Id: namespaceState.xml,v 1.5 2006/01/03 18:35:35 NormanWalsh Exp $?>
<header>
<title>The Disposition of Names in an XML Namespace</title>
<w3c-designation>&http-ident;-&iso6.doc.date;</w3c-designation>
<w3c-doctype>TAG Finding</w3c-doctype>
<pubdate><day>&draft.day;</day>
<month>&draft.monthname;</month>
<year>&draft.year;</year>
</pubdate>
<publoc>
<loc href="&http-ident;-&iso6.doc.date;.html">&http-ident;-&iso6.doc.date;</loc>
</publoc>
<altlocs>
<loc href="&http-ident;-&iso6.doc.date;.xml">XML</loc>
</altlocs>
<latestloc>
<loc href="&http-ident;.html">&http-ident;</loc>
</latestloc>
<prevlocs>
<loc href="&http-ident;-2005-12-16.html">&http-ident;-2005-12-16</loc>
</prevlocs>
<authlist>
<author><name>Norman Walsh</name>
<affiliation>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</affiliation>
<email href="mailto:Norman.Walsh@Sun.COM">Norman.Walsh@Sun.COM</email></author>
</authlist>

<abstract>
<p>This Finding addresses the question of whether or not adding new
names to a (published) namespace is a sound practice.</p>
</abstract>

<status>

<p>This document has been produced by the
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/2001/tag/">W3C Technical Architecture Group (TAG)</loc>.
This finding addresses TAG issue
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/2001/tag/ilist#nameSpaceState-48">nameSpaceState-48</loc>.
The TAG approved this finding at its
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/2001/tag/2006/01/03-minutes.html#action01">3&#160;January&#160;2006 teleconference</loc>.
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/2001/tag/findings">Additional TAG findings</loc>,
both approved and in draft state, may also
be available.</p>

<p>Please send comments on this finding to the publicly archived TAG
mailing list www-tag@w3.org
(<loc href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-tag/">archive</loc>).
</p>

<p>The terms <rfc2119>MUST</rfc2119>, <rfc2119>SHOULD</rfc2119>, and
<rfc2119>SHOULD NOT</rfc2119> are used in this document
in accordance with <bibref ref="rfc2119"/>.</p>

<p>Please send comments on this finding to the publicly archived TAG
mailing list <loc
href="mailto:www-tag@w3.org">www-tag@w3.org</loc>
(<loc
href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-tag/">archive</loc>).</p>

</status>
<pubstmt>
<p>Chicago, Vancouver, Mountain View, et al.: World-Wide Web Consortium,
Draft TAG Finding, 2005.</p>
</pubstmt>
<sourcedesc>
<p>Created in electronic form.</p>
</sourcedesc>
<langusage>
<language id="EN">English</language>
</langusage>
<revisiondesc>
<slist>
<sitem>2005-09-13: Published draft</sitem>
</slist>
</revisiondesc>
</header>
<body>

<div1 id="preface">
<head>Preface</head>

<p>Namespaces are a mechanism for managing names in a distributed way that
greatly reduces the likelihood that two independent parties will create
the same name for different purposes.</p>

<p>An XML namespace has a namespace name (a URI) and a set of local names
(<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/#NT-NCName">NCName</loc>s as
defined in <bibref ref="xml-names"/>). Using a URI leverages the
well-understood <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/#uri-assignment">URI
allocation</loc> mechanisms of <bibref ref="webarch"/>.
<bibref ref="xml-names"/> defines a syntactic shorthand for the combination
of a namespace name and a local name: the qualified name, or “QName”.
(Note that languages which use QNames as identifiers 
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/#qname-mapping">are required</loc>
to provide a mapping from QNames to URIs.)</p>

<p>The proposal to define a new local name, “<code>id</code>”, in
the namespace “<code>http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace</code>” (the
<code>xml:</code> namespace) raised a question about the identity
of a namespace. Concretely, it exposed two perspectives:</p>

<olist>
<item><p>One perspective was that the
<code>xml:</code> namespace consisted of <code>xml:space</code>,
<code>xml:lang</code>, and <code>xml:base</code> (and no other names)
because there was a point in time in which those where the only three
names from that namespace that had a defined meaning.</p>
</item>
<item><p>The other
perspective was that the <code>xml:</code> namespace consisted of all
possible local names and that only a finite (but flexible) number of
them are defined at any given point in time.</p>
</item>
</olist>

<p>Colloquially, we often speak of “adding a name” to a namespace.
Here we prefer to speak of “defining a name” or otherwise licensing
the interpretation of a name. For example, the <bibref ref="xml-id"/>
specification defines the meaning of the local name “id” in the
<code>xml:</code> namespace. Similarly, a namespace created to hold
the names of all the reserved words in a programming language would
license the interpretation of those QNames without explicitly defining
each of them.</p>
</div1>

<div1 id="namespacedef">
<head>Namespace Definitions</head>

<p>The publication of <bibref ref="xml-id"/> as a
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/Process-20040205/tr.html#RecsW3C">Recommendation</loc>,
provided a partial answer to the question of which perspective is
correct. Adding a definition for the local name “<code>id</code>” in the
<code>xml:</code> namespace demonstrated that the number of local names
defined in the <code>xml:</code> namespace could be extended.</p>

<p>The question remains, however, as to whether the other position is
ever sound. This Finding takes the position that it is.</p>

<p>Namespaces, originally designed to provide names for XML elements
and attributes, have been adopted much more broadly by the web
community. They are now used not simply for elements and attributes
but for function names, tokens, and identifiers for ever more
purposes.</p>

<p>The <code>xml:</code> namespace demonstrates that some namespaces
benefit from a policy that allows additional names to be defined in them
over time. This does not preclude the possibility that some
namespaces would benefit from a policy that forbids such extension.
From these observations, we conclude that the following good practice
applies:</p>

<p role="practice">Specifications that define namespaces
<rfc2119>SHOULD</rfc2119> explicitly state their policy with respect
to changes in the names defined in that namespace.
</p>
</div1>

<p>For namespaces that are not immutable, the specification
<rfc2119>SHOULD</rfc2119> describe how names may be given definitions
(or have them removed) and by whom.</p>

<p>If a namespace document is provided, as
<bibref ref="webarch"/> recommends, the namespace change policy
<rfc2119>SHOULD</rfc2119> be stated in the namespace document.
</p>

<p>As a general rule, resources on the web can and do change. In the
absence of an explicit statement, one cannot infer that a namespace
is immutable.</p>

<div1 id="references">
<head>References</head>

<blist>
<bibl id="rfc2119" href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt" key="RFC 2119">S.
Bradner. <titleref>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</titleref>.
IETF. March, 1997.</bibl>

<bibl id="xml-names" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/"
key="XML Namespaces">Tim Bray, Dave Hollander, Andrew Layman, editors.
<titleref>Namespaces in XML</titleref>.
World Wide Web Consortium, 1999.</bibl>

<bibl id="webarch" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/" key="WebArch Vol 1">Ian Jacobs and Norman Walsh, editors.
<titleref>Architecture of the World Wide Web, Volume 1</titleref>.
World Wide Web Consortium, 2004.
</bibl>

<bibl id="xml-id" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-id/" key="xml:id">Jonathan Marsh, Daniel Veillard, and Norman Walsh, editors.
<titleref>xml:id Version 1.0</titleref>.
World Wide Web Consortium, 2005.
</bibl>
</blist>
</div1>
</body>
</spec>
